<!-- -*-mode: xml-*- -->
<help language="en">
  <section id="help-on-command" prompt="Command description">
    <call function="lyskom-help-on-command" />
  </section>

  <section id="commands" prompt="Keyboard commands">
    <p>Keyboard commands:</p>
    <keymap />
  </section>

  <section id="language-help" prompt="">
    <h2>Language Settings</h2>

    <p>
      You can switch the language in this session by using the command
      <cref id="kom-change-language" /> or the Emacs command <i>M-x
      kom-change-language</i>. To also change the key bindings (this
      will affect all sessions), type C-u before the command (e.g. C-u
      x<cref id="kom-change-language" />).
    </p>

    <p>
      For full information, including how to change the default
      language, see <refer id="language" /> (this information will be
      presented using the current language selection).
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="language" prompt="Language">
    <h1>Multiple language support</h1>

    <p>
      The elisp client can be built to support multiple languages. The
      default is to build with support for english and swedish, with
      english as the default language selection.
    </p>

    <h2>Temporary Language Change</h2>

    <p>
      Use <cref id="kom-change-language" /> to temporarily switch
      languages. Please note that you must give a prefix argument to
      <cref id="kom-change-language" /> to change the key binding.
      Key bindings are changed in <i>all</i> sessions, not just the
      one where the command is given.
    </p>

    <h2>Permanent Language Change</h2>

    <p>
      Use <cref id="kom-customize" /> to change languages permanently.
      By saving the language selection in .emacs, that language will
      be the default the next time you start Emacs and load the elisp
      client.
    </p>

    <h2>Changing the default language</h2>

    <p>
      There are a number of ways to change the default language in the
      elisp client. The client looks at the following, in order, until
      it finds a useful setting:
    </p>

    <list>
      <item>The variable kom-default-language (change it with <cref
      id="kom-customize" />)</item>

      <item>The environment variable KOMLANGUAGE</item>

      <item>The environment variable LC_ALL</item>

      <item>The environment variable LC_MESSAGES</item>

      <item>The environment variable LANG</item>
    </list>

    <p>
      The variable kom-default-language can be set to a list of
      symbols, where each symbol corresponds to a language. Se the
      list below for available languages. The first language on the
      list that is supported by the client will be used.
    </p>

    <p>
      The environment variables should be set to a language code. For
      example, the value "sv" will cause the client to use Swedish.
    </p>

    <h2>Known languages</h2>

    <list>
      <item>sv - Swedish</item>
      <item>en - English</item>
    </list>

  </section>

  <section id="conferences" prompt="Conferences">

    <h1>Conferences</h1>

    <p>
      Every LysKOM system is organized as a set of conferences, each
      covering a separate topic. Anybody can create a conference, but
      you should think twice before doing so. In a mature LysKOM
      system the conference you want to create probably already
      exists.
    </p>

    <p>
      Conferences can be open, closed and secret. Anyone can join and
      read texts in all open conferences. To join a closed conference,
      the conference administractor has to grant membership. Secret
      conferences are secret: you can't even see them unless you're a
      member. Most conferences are open. Closed and secret conferences
      are much less common.
    </p>

    <p>
      The following commands might be useful to get started:
    </p>

    <inline id="kom-list-conferences" />
    <inline id="kom-review-presentation" />
    <inline id="kom-add-self" />
    <inline id="kom-go-to-conf" />

    <h2>Priorities</h2>

    <p>
      Your memberships have priorities. When you log on, conferences
      with higher priority will be presented before conferences with
      lower priority. Use <cref id="kom-prioritize" /> to change your
      priorities.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="persons" prompt="Persons">
    <h1>Persons</h1>

    <p>
      Every LysKOM user has a person. A person contains some
      statistics about what the user has done (texts created, texts
      read, logon time, and some other stuff). Every person is also
      associated with a letterbox with the same name of the person.
      The letterbox is essentially a regular closed conference.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="texts" prompt="Texts">
    <h1>Texts</h1>

    <p>
      The purpose of LysKOM is to communicate, and communication is
      done through texts. Texts are simply texts written by a LysKOM
      member.
    </p>

    <h2>Recipients</h2>

    <p>
      Every text has one or more recipients: conferences to which the
      text has been sent. There are three kinds of recipients: regular
      recipients, cc-recipients and bcc-recipients.
    </p>

    <p>
      <b>Regular recipients</b> are the most common. A regular
      recipient means that the text belongs in the specified
      conference (or conferences). Comments to the text will
      automatically be sent to the same set of recipients.
    </p>

    <p>
      <b>CC recipients</b> are used when you want to send a copy of a
      text to a conference, but don't want followups sent to that
      conference.
    </p>

    <p>
      <b>BCC recipients</b> are fairly unusual. To even <i>see</i> a
      BCC recipient you have to have permission to be a member in the
      recipient conference. This kind of recipient can be used when
      you want to send a copy of a text to somebody's letterbox, but
      don't want other readers to know.
    </p>

    <h2>Comments</h2>

    <p>
      A text can have comments. A thread of comments to comments to
      comments is often called comment thread, comment chain or
      comment tree (strictly speaking a comment thread is a path down
      the comment tree). Anyone can write comments to any text. There
      is not requirement that comments be sent to the same conferences
      as the commented texts.    </p>

    <h2>Special texts</h2>

    <p>
      There are three kinds of special texts: presentations, FAQs and
      notices. A presentation is a text associated with a conference
      or letterbox, that contains a presentation of that conference or
      person. These are normally sent to special conferences. A FAQ is
      a text with frequently asked questions (and answers) in a
      particular conference. Normally, new FAQs will be displayed when
      entering the associated conference. Notices are texts that
      contain urgent information about a person or conference. You can
      use a notice when you will be away from LysKOM for a while, and
      similar occasions.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="settings" prompt="Settings">
    <h1>Settings</h1>

    <p>
      The elisp client has a large number of user-configurable
      settings. With a few exceptions you can change these by using
      the command <cref id="kom-customize" />.
    </p>

    <p>
      Settings can be saved in the server or in your .emacs. Settings
      that are saved in the server will apply only for a particular
      user on a particular server. Settings saved in .emacs take
      precedence over settings stored in the server.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="reading" prompt="Reading texts">
    <h1>Reading texts</h1>

    <p>
      To just read texts in the default order, simply press SPC until
      all texts have been displayed. The elisp client will display one
      text at a time until you have read all texts in all conferences
      you are a member of. Use the command <cref id="kom-list-summary"
      /> to see which texts will be shown. There are a large number of
      more advanced commands, some of which are listed in the sections
      mentioned below.
    </p>

    <list header="See also:">
      <item><refer id="filter" /></item>
      <item><refer id="review" /></item>
      <item><refer id="mark" /></item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section id="filter" prompt="Avoiding certain texts">
    <h1>Avoiding certain texts</h1>

    <p>
      Sometimes you don't want to read certain texts. In those cases
      the following commands may be useful. Besides these, there are a
      number of commands for filtering texts, if there is a certain
      type of text you never want to see.
    </p>

    <inline id="kom-set-unread" />
    <inline id="kom-jump" />
    <inline id="kom-super-jump" />
  </section>

  <section id="mark" prompt="Remembering texts">
    <h1>Remembering texts</h1>

    <p>
      Sometimes you might find a text that you want to remember. In
      these cases, mark the text. A mark is really just a number from
      0 to 255, but the elisp client supports assigning
      easy-to-remember names to marks.
    </p>

    <inline id="kom-mark-text" />
    <inline id="kom-unmark-text" />
    <inline id="kom-review-all-marked-texts" />
    <inline id="kom-review-marked-texts" />
    <inline id="kom-list-marks" />
  </section>

  <section id="review" prompt="Finding old texts">
    <h1>Finding old texts</h1>

    <p>
      There are a large number of commands for finding old texts. All
      of these start with the word "Review". This is just a small
      sampling:
    </p>

    <inline id="kom-review-by-to" />
    <inline id="kom-review-first" />
    <inline id="kom-review-more" />
    <inline id="kom-review-clear" />
    <inline id="kom-view-commented-text" />
    <inline id="kom-review-comments" />
    <inline id="kom-find-root-review" />
    <inline id="kom-find-root" />
    <inline id="kom-review-tree" />
  </section>

  <section id="writing" prompt="Writing or changing texts">
    <h1>Writing or changing texts</h1>

    <p>
      There are three basic types of texts: texts, comments and
      footnotes. All of them are texts, but they are associated to
      <i>other</i> texts in different ways.
    </p>

    <h2>Texts</h2>

    <p>
      These are texts that aren't comments to other texts. They start
      a new thread of discussion. Remember to choose a good subject
      line when you create new texts.
    </p>

    <inline id="kom-write-text" />
    <inline id="kom-send-letter" />

    <h2>Comments</h2>

    <p>
      Comments are texts that are comments to other texts. When you
      write a comment, check that the subject line and recipients are
      still suitable. Personal replies are simply comments sent to
      somebody's letterbox.
    </p>

    <inline id="kom-write-comment" />
    <inline id="kom-private-answer" />

    <h2>Footnotes</h2>

    <p>
      Footnotes are special comments that only the author of a text
      can create. Since they are presented before regular comments,
      they are useful when you want to clarify something you've
      written before people start writing comments to the text.
    </p>

    <inline id="kom-write-footnote" />

    <h2>Prefix argument</h2>

    <p>
      There are several ways to specify which text you want to comment
      or write a footnote to. When you give any of the comments listed
      above without an argument, they will apply to the most recenty
      read text.
    </p>

    <p>
      Sometimes you want a different text. There are a few commands
      that apply to the next-to-most-recently read (<cref
      id="kom-comment-previous" />, <cref
      id="kom-private-answer-previous" />), and by using prefix
      arguments you can specify any text to any command. Supply a
      prefix argument as usual in Emacs by C-u followed by the
      argument, or simply type the argument directly.
    </p>

    <p>
      Specify text <i>N</i> by giving the text number as the prefix
      argument. Specify the text where the cursor is by giving prefix
      argument 0. Specify the text <i>N</i> texts back in the buffer
      from the point where the cursor is by giving the prefix argument
      -<i>N</i>. To get a prompt at which you can type the text
      number, simply hit C-u before giving the command.
    </p>

    <h2>Manage recipients</h2>

    <p>
      To change the recipients on a text you have to be the author of
      the text or administrator of the recipient you want to change.
      Use the commands <cref id="kom-add-recipient" /> to add and
      <cref id="kom-sub-recipient" /> to remove recipients.
    </p>

    <h2>Messages and remarks</h2>

    <p>
      Never use messages (personal, group or alarm messages) or
      remarks in place of regular texts. It won't work and people will
      get upset.
    </p>
  </section>


  <section id="kom-list-conferences" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-list-conferences" /></h3>

    <p>
      List conferences in LysKOM. Use this command with creative
      arguments to find conferences that you're interested in.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-list-re" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-list-re" /></h3>

    <p>
      List conferences in LysKOM. Use this command with creative
      arguments to find conferences that you're interested in.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-presentation" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-presentation" /></h3>

    <p>
      Show the presentation for a conference or person. Use this
      command to get more information about a conference.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-add-self" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-add-self" /></h3>

    <p>
      Join a conference so you can read the texts in the conference
      and so you'll find out when new texts are created.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-go-to-conf" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-go-to-conf" /></h3>

    <p>
      Go to a conference you want to read texts in. If you aren't
      already a member of the conference, you will be asked if you
      want to join the conference.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-write-footnote" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-write-footnote" /></h3>

    <p>
      Creates a new footnote to an existing text.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-private-answer" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-private-answer" /></h3>

    <p>
      Creates a private reply to the author of an existing text.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-write-comment" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-write-comment" /></h3>

    <p>
      Creates a new comment to an existing text.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-send-letter" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-send-letter" /></h3>

    <p>
      Creates a new letter.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-write-text" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-write-text" /></h3>

    <p>
      Creates a new text that is not a comment to any other text.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-tree" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-tree" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews the entire tree of comments under the specified text.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-find-root" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-find-root" /></h3>

    <p>
      Finds the text that started the discussion that the specified
      text is part of.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-find-root-review" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-find-root-review" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews the entire tree of comments that the specified text is
      part of. Essentially the same as doing <cref id="kom-find-root"
      /> followed by <cref id="kom-review-tree" />.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-comments" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-comments" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews all comments to the specified text, but not the comments
      to the comments.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-view-commented-text" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-view-commented-text" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews the text to which the specified text is a comment.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-clear" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-clear" /></h3>

    <p>
      Aborts all review commands that are active.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-more" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-more" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews more texts using the same criteria as the most recent
      <cref id="kom-review-by-to" />, or <cref id="kom-review-first"
      /> command.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-first" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-first" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews the first text(s) created by a particular person sent to
      a particular conference. Any parameter can be ignored by simply
      not supplying a value (use zero for the number of texts) in
      order to do things like review all texts to a particular
      conference, the first five texts written by a particular person
      and so forth.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-by-to" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-by-to" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews the text(s) most recently created by a particular person
      sent to a particular conference. Any parameter can be ignored by
      simply not supplying a value (use zero for the number of texts)
      in order to do things like review all texts to a particular
      conference, the last five texts written by a particular person
      and so forth.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-list-marks" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-list-marks" /></h3>

    <p>
      Lists all texts marked with a particular mark.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-marked-texts" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-marked-texts" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews all texts marked with a particular mark.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-review-all-marked-texts" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-review-all-marked-texts" /></h3>

    <p>
      Reviews all marked texts.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-unmark-text" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-unmark-text" /></h3>

    <p>
      Removes your marks from a texts.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-mark-text" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-mark-text" /></h3>

    <p>
      Marks a texts. Normally this command will ask for the mark to
      use.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-super-jump" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-super-jump" /></h3>

    <p>
      Creates a filter that will skip texts that have the same subject
      line as the specified text and are sent to the current
      conference.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-jump" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-jump" /></h3>

    <p>
      Skips all texts in the comment tree below the most recently read
      text. This is useful when you see a text that starts a
      discussion that you aren't interested in.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-set-unread" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-set-unread" /></h3>

    <p>
      Set the number of unread texts in a particular conference. Can
      be useful when you have lots of old texts to catch up with.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section id="kom-prioritize" prompt="">
    <h3><cref id="kom-prioritize" /></h3>

    <p>
      Interactively change priorities and placements of your
      memberships. For more information, press C-h m or ? when you
      have given the command.
    </p>
  </section>
</help>
