<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                      "docbook/dtd/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % fnc SYSTEM "fnc.ent">
  <!ENTITY % var SYSTEM "var.ent">

  %fnc;   <!-- LysKOM functions -->
  %var;   <!-- LysKOM variables -->
]>

<book lang="en">
  <chapter id="chapter:etiquette">
        <title>Etiquette</title>

        <para>
          Do not add more conferences as recipients to a text than is
          necessary. Although a text may be relevant to the topic of
          several conferences, it may not be appropriate in all of
          them. Think before you act.
        </para>

        <para>
          There are some rules of etiquette that apply to recipients.
          The rules may vary from LysKOM system to LysKOM system, but
          here these guidelines are unlikely to get you into trouble.
        </para>

        <para>
          When moving a text from one conference to another, or when
          you write a comment and decide that one of the default
          recipients isn't relevant any more, leave the original
          recipient as a carbon copy recipient. This ensures that
          members of the original recipient will have a chance to
          notice the move.
        </para>

        <para>
          Do not add people's mailboxes as recipients without
          thinking. The client will sometimes add letterboxes
          automatically or semi-automatically when appropriate.
        </para>

        <para>
          Do not <emphasis>remove</emphasis> people's mailboxes as
          recipients, or convert them to carbon copy recipients when
          writing comments. It is up to the user themselves to do
          this. Most of the time, when a letterbox appears as a
          recipient, it is because the person in question isn't a
          member of any of regular recipients of the text, but still
          wants to participate in the discussion.
        </para>
  </chapter>
</book>

