<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                      "docbook/dtd/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % fnc SYSTEM "fnc.ent">
  <!ENTITY % var SYSTEM "var.ent">

  %fnc;   <!-- LysKOM functions -->
  %var;   <!-- LysKOM variables -->
]>

<book lang="en">
  <chapter>
    <title>Texts in LysKOM</title>

    <para>
    </para>

    <section id="texts:special">
      <title>Special Texts</title>

      <section id="texts:presentations">
        <title>Presentations</title>

        <para>
          Every conference and person can and should have a
          presentation. A conference presentation should contain
          information about the conference, such as what topics are
          appropriate, related conferences and possibly external
          links. Do not confuse presentations with FAQs; there is
          support for FAQ texts as well (<xref linkend="texts:faqs"
          />).
        </para>

        <para>
          Keeping with the tradition of openness, presentations of
          persons in LysKOM are fairly detailed, almost always
          including the real name and location of the person, and
          frequently including telephone number, address, interests,
          job details and more.
        </para>

        <para>
          You can see the presentation for any conference or person
          using &fn:kom-review-presentation;. To change or create a
          presentation for a person or conference, use
          &fn:kom-change-presentation;. You can remove a presentation
          using &fn:kom-remove-presentation;. To make an existing text
          the presentation of a conference, use
          &fn:kom-set-presentation;.
        </para>

        <para>
          When you use &fn:kom-change-presentation; to create the
          presentation for a conference or person, the recipient of
          that text will be a special conference (there is one for
          conferences and one for persons). If the conference is
          secret, the recipient will be the conference itself since
          there is no point in presenting a secret conference.
        </para>

        <para>
          When you use &fn:kom-change-presentation; to change a
          presentation the new presentation will be a comment to the
          old one. This is a convention that helps people see what
          differs from one presentation to the next.
        </para>

        <para>
          Presentations are protected from automatic deletion, but can
          be deleted manually. Don't do that.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="texts:notices">
        <title>Notices</title>

        <para>
          A notice is a text containing important information about
          the server, a person or a conference. Each object can have
          at most one notice. Notices are sent to a special
          conference. Check the recipient of your notice if it is
          applied to a secret conference; the conference will be less
          secret if its notice is in a public conference.
        </para>

        <para>
          Notices are protected from automatic deletion but can be
          deleted manually. Don't do that. If you want to remove a
          notice, use the appropriate command (see below).
        </para>

        <simplesect id="texts:notices:server">
          <title>Server notices</title>

          <para>
            The server notice (sometimes called "message of the day")
            is shown on login and can be reviewed by using the
            &fn:kom-status-server;; the text number of the server
            notice will be listed.
          </para>

          <para>
            The server notice is set using the &fn:kom-set-motd; and
            removed with &fn:kom-remove-motd; These commands are only
            available in administrative mode.
          </para>
        </simplesect>


        <simplesect id="texts:notices:conf">
          <title>Conference notices</title>

          <para>
            Conference notices are not used in this client. They can
            be set and removed by the conference supervisor using
            &fn:kom-change-conf-motd; and &fn:kom-unset-conf-motd;,
            respectively.
          </para>
        </simplesect>

        <simplesect id="texts:notices:pers">
          <title>Person notices</title>

          <para>
            Notices may be attached to letterboxes. In a strictly
            technical sense, these notices are conference notices, but
            from the perspective of the user they are different. When
            writing a text with a lettterbox as a recipient, any
            notice on that letterbox will be shown, and confirmation
            is required to submit the text.
          </para>

          <para>
            Person notices are set and removed by the conference
            supervisor using &fn:kom-change-conf-motd; and
            &fn:kom-unset-conf-motd;, respectively.
          </para>
        </simplesect>

      </section>

      <section id="texts:faqs">
        <title>FAQs</title>

        <para>
          A FAQ is a regular text that is linked to one or more
          conferences through a FAQ link. The purpose of a FAQ is to
          answer questions that are frequently asked in the
          conference. If the list of questions is small, it is not
          uncommon to use the conference presentation instead. It is
          also possible to attach a FAQ to the server itself.
        </para>

        <para>
          A FAQ is considered unread as a FAQ until you read it using
          one of the special FAQ-related commands in the context of a
          particular conference. If a text you have read is added as a
          FAQ to a conference, it will become an unread FAQ for that
          conference, and will be shown the next time you enter the
          conference. If it is later added as a FAQ to another
          conference, it will become an unread FAQ for
          <emphasis>that</emphasis> conference, despite the face that
          you have read it twice.
        </para>

        <para>
          With default settings, unread FAQs are listed and shown each
          time you enter a conference or log on to the server. When
          you enter a conference, FAQs that are unread in that
          conference are listed and shown. When you log on to the
          server, unread FAQs that are attached to the server are
          listed.
        </para>

        <para>
          To list all FAQs that are attached to a conference, use
          &fn:kom-status-conf; (FAQs are listed as part of the status)
          or &fn:kom-review-presentation; (in which case FAQs are
          listed after the conference presentation). To list all
          conferences attached to the server, use
          &fn:kom-status-server; (FAQs are listed as part of the
          status).
        </para>

        <para>
          To view FAQs for a particular conference, use
          &fn:kom-review-faq;. To view FAQs for the server, use
          &fn:kom-review-server-faq;.
        </para>

        <para>
          In the elisp client the link is created with one of the
          commands &fn:kom-add-faq; or &fn:kom-change-conf-faq;, and is
          removed using &fn:kom-del-faq;. There are similar commands
          for manipulating server FAQs; these can only be used by
          users with administrative rights to the LysKOM server.
        </para>
        
        <para>
          There are a number of settings that affect FAQs.
          &var:kom-auto-list-faqs; controls automatic listing of FAQs
          when entering conferences. &var:kom-auto-review-faqs;
          controls automatic reviewing of FAQs when entering
          conferences.
        </para>

      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
